Couple things to get you started.
While nutrition is an
important consideration here,
I need to make sure that
it's completely clear here.
Resistance exercise is by
far the greater stimuli
of muscle growth relative to nutrition.
Really from this perspective,
we need to make sure we
have sufficient calories,
which is to be said as hyper caloric.
So we need a little bit more
calories and we're burning.
Does this stay alive?
And mostly we need to
focus on protein here.
1.6 grams per kilogram
of body weight is a great place to start.
Now I personally prefer
a little bit higher,
2.2 grams per kilogram, which
is about one gram per pound.
But actually I believe the
science is pretty clear here.
Suggesting that going from 1.6
to 2.2 is not really going
to increase the amount
of muscle you're you're growing.
And if it is, it's not
going to be by much.
And so, if you prefer to
be at 1.6, that's fine.
Higher is absolutely okay as well
and it may aid in some
people in some circumstances.
But going below 1.6 seems
to reduce the amount
of muscle you can grow.
So we want to be at least that number.
From a training perspective,
you want to start by focusing
on your big muscle groups.
Now if you have a particular muscle
or group of muscles that
you want to increase
for any number of reasons, say
you've identified assymetry,
have a personal preference,
you enjoy that more,
you just want to have a
muscle group grow larger
for some aesthetic reasons,
that's absolutely fine.
Focus on those.
But you really shouldn't
omit everything else either.
It's critically important
to maintain posture
and joint integrity
by ensuring we have adequate
muscle surrounding each joint.
Which basically means we need
to address each muscle at some
point throughout the week.
We can certainly emphasize
some more than others.
That's no problem whatsoever.
But we don't want to leave big chunks
of muscles completely unchallenged.
That's going to present
problems more likely if not now,
down the road.
So we also want to challenge these muscles
across multiple stimuli,
meaning exercises.
So whether you prefer your body
weight, machines, dumbbells,
kettlebells, or any number
of other strategies,
those are absolutely fine.
All are incredibly effective.
And at the highest level,
it actually doesn't
really matter that much
which of those strategies you try,
because at the end of the day
it's just about stimulating the muscle.
However you go about
that is absolutely fine.
So you have lots of options there.
Perhaps in a future episode
we'll get into the the details
and spend the entire discussion
on that going over pros
and cons of those different
strategies and tactics.
But for now at at again
the most zoomed out level,
you've got a tremendous amount of options
regarding which exercise
you select and which modes
and methodologies you do to
engage that resistance exercise.
The range of motion is critical.
You want to use the largest range
of motion you can while still being safe
and protective of both
the exercising joint
as well as the joint
above it and below it.
So an example here,
let's just say you're interested
in growing your quadriceps.
You want to have a lot of
activity over both the knee
and hip joint, but you want to make sure
that you're doing though that in a case
in which you're not
compromising your low back
and say your feet.
And so making sure we're
protecting the joints above
and below the muscle group
is important as well.
So we really want to challenge our muscles
as much as we can in a
variety of ways there.
In terms of how much to
do the repetitions per set
doesn't really matter,
such that you can have success
in a number of them anywhere
between, say as low as
five repetitions per set,
all the way up to 30 or
more repetitions per set
can be equally effective
for muscle growth.
The total amount of sets per week
is probably the bigger determinant.
From there, you probably want
to be in the neighborhood
of about 15 to 20 working
sets per muscle per week.
If you were to break that down,
let's say you were focusing again
on your hamstrings muscles,
if you did three sets on day one,
three sets on day two
and three sets on day three,
that would give you a total
of nine working sets per week.
That's probably a little bit too low.
But if you did two hamstring
exercises each day,
three sets each, that'd
be six sets day one,
six sets day two, six sets day three,
and now you're up to close
the 18 working sets per per week rather.
That's a pretty good spot to be in.
Lots of things we could
talk about there in terms
of advanced athletes and elite,
but structurally
and roughly that's going
to put you in the ballpark.
That's going to be enough stimulus
for most people to grow most of the time.
Last consideration here is frequency,
as I sort of alluded to
here, somewhere between two
to three days per week per
muscle group is a great way
to go about it.
More is fine as well if you
can handle the recovery.
Less than two days a week is
also theoretically possible.
There's excellent research
showing one day a week
per muscle group is sufficient
in muscle to grow muscle.
It does become practically
challenging though,
because now you've got to fit
all those working sets into a single day.
And that is challenging both
in the length of the workout
as well as how sore and
how much damage you create.
So what I recommend here is
what I call the 72 hour rule,
which is every seven two hours
or so work each of your muscles
to a nice pump or contraction.
Remember, we want to
stimulate muscle growth here,
but we don't want to
annihilate the muscle either.
Excessive fatigue and damage
and soreness does not aid
in muscle growth and can
actually harm our ability
to come back and train
again in the next session,
or even the one following that,
which would then reduce
our overall total volume.
So enough intensity, enough
difficulty to stimulate growth,
but not so much that we
completely annihilate it.
We got to be able to repeat
that every 72 hours or so.
So, again the way I say
it, take it to a nice pump,
a nice contraction,
whatever that means to you.
And that's going to get a lot of people
in a close enough ballpark
to growing muscle.
[music]